Register of the Russia. Voennyĭ Agent (Japan) Records
Hoover Institution Archives
- File No. 42. Correspondence of the Supervisor for the Inspection of Quartermaster Stores in Japan (Captain Popovskii) with the Quarter master of the Vladivostok Fortress, the Director of the Vladivostok Quartermaster's Storage Depot for Imported Goods, the District Quartermaster of the Amur Military District, Okura & Co., Ltd., and the Syndicate of Military Boots Manufacturers in Japan, including letters, telegrams, reports, acts, information sheets, declarations, position paper, and protocols, 1916-1917, concerning shortages or deficiencies in shipments of military supplies (boots, underwear, ammunition pouches, etc.) and negotiations for reductions in price due to these deficiencies. (Folder 9: 5)
- File No. 43. Correspondence of the Supervisor for the Inspection of Quartermaster Stores in Japan (Captain Popovskii) with the Supervisor of the Vladivostok Storage Depot, the Russian Military Attaché in Japan, the District Quartermaster of the Amur Military District, and various Japanese firms, including letters, telegrams, and reports, 1917-1918, concerning: 1) shortages in shipments of military supplies (boots, ammunition pouches, underwear, etc.) purchased from Japanese frims, discovered upon the unloading and inspection of these shipments in Vladivostok; 2) special missions undertaken by the Russian military inspectors. (Folder 9: 6)
- File No. 44. Correspondence of the Supervisor for the Inspection of Quartermaster Stores in Japan (Colonel Popovskii) with the Russian Military Attaché in Japan (Colonel Podtiagin), the Quartermaster of the Vladivostok Fortress, the District Quartermaster of the Amur Military District, and the Special Representative of the Minister of Supply and Provisioning of the All-Russian Government, including letters, telegrams, acts, information sheets, signed statements, declarations, reports, inquiries, invoices, freight bills, agreements, and minutes, 1919, concerning: 1) the unloading and inspection after their arrival in Vladivostok of military supplies purchased from Japanese firms, and problems connected with boxes in these shipments not bearing an inspector's stamp; 2) instructions of the Russian Military Attaché relative to inspection procedures; 3) contracts negotiated by the Special Representative of the Ministry of Supply; 4) reports on inspection procedures. (Box-folder 10: 1-2)
- File No. 45. Correspondence of the Representative of the Quartermaster's Department in Japan (Colonel Popovskii) with the Russian Military Attaché in Japan (Major-General Podtiagin) and the Special Representative of the Minister of Supply and Provisioning (B. K. Ianovskii), including letters, telegrams, receipts, acts, minutes, and tables, 1919-1920, concerning the reception and inspection of military supplies (shirts, cloth, telegraph tape) purchased from Japanese firms. (Folder 10: 3)
- File No. 46. Correspondence of the subordinate to the Military Attaché in Japan (Major-General Podtiagin), including letters, telegrams, receipts, acts, lists, and specification, 1921, relative to the shipment of medical and veterinary supplies stored in the warehouses of the Russian Volunteer Fleet and in those of Nagayanagi & Co.; and to the termination of the office of Supervisor for the Inspection of Quartermaster Stores in Japan. (Folder 10: 4)
- File No. 47. Account book of the Supervisor for the Inspection of Quartermaster Stores in Japan (Colonel Popovskii), listing income and expenditures for the period 1914-1922. (Folder 10: 5)
- File No. 48. Correspondence of the Russian Military Attaché in Japan and the Chairman of the Commission for the Reception of Artillery Supplies Ordered in Japan with the Chief Ordnance Administration, the firm of Bryner, Kousnezoff & Co., and other offices and individuals, including letters, telegrams, reports, instructions, lists, information sheets, contracts, certificates, and agreements, 1915-1917, relative to the purchase of 4,000,000 22-second distance fuses from Bryner, Kousnezoff & Co. according to contract no. 5705. Part 1. (Folder 10: 6)
- File No. 49. Correspondence of the Russian Military Attaché in Japan with Bryner, Kousnezoff & Co. and the Russian Embassy in Tokyo including letters, telegrams, reports, and lists, 1916-1918, relative to the purchase of 4,000,000 22-second distance fuses from Bryner, Kousnezoff & Co. according to contract no. 5705. Part 2. (Box-folder 11: 1)
- File No. 50. Correspondence of the Russian Military Attaché in Japan (Colonel Morel) with the Japanese War and Naval Ministries, Bryner, Kousnezoff & Co., and various Japanese firms, including letters, telegrams, reports, requests, and estimates, 1916, concerning the purchase of 4,000,000 22-second distance fuses for shrapnel from Bryner, Kousnezoff & Co. according to contract no. 5705, and to the acquisition of materials (black powder, aluminum, etc.) used to manufacture these fuses. (Folder 11: 2)
- File No. 51. Correspondence of the Chairman of the Commission for the Reception of Artillery Supplies Ordered in Japan (Lieutenant-General Somoff) with the Chief Ordnance Administration, the Banque Russo-Asiatique, and other members of the Commission, including letters, reports, accounts, receipts, attestations, lists, and telegrams, 1916-1917, concerning salaries for the members of the Commission, and the withdrawal and reception of the required sums. (Folder 11: 3)
- File No. 52. Correspondence of the Senior Tester and Technical Consultant of the Artillery Committee of the Chief Ordnance Administration (Colonel Podtiagin) with the Chief Artillery Administration, the Chief of Artillery at the Vladivostok Fortress, and other individuals and offices, including letters, telegrams, instructions, tables, information sheets, lists, and reports, 1915-1916, concerning technical characteristics of artillery supplies purchased in Japan, and providing information on shipments of, and contracts for, these supplies. (Folder 11: 4)
- File No. 53. Correspondence of the Chairman of the Commission for the Inspection of Artillery Supplies Ordered in Japan (Lieutenant-General Somoff) and of the Senior Tester and Technical Consultant of the Artillery Committee of the Chief Ordnance Administration (Colonel Podtiagin) with the Chief Ordnance Administration, various members of the Commission, and Japanese firms, including letters, telegrams, reports, lists, receipts, certificates, invoices and information sheets, 1916-1917, concerning the fulfillment of orders for artillery supplies, the reception and testing of these supplies, and the payment of salaries to members of the Commission. (Box-folder 12: 1)
- File No. 54. Correspondence of the Chairman of the Commission for the Reception of Artillery Supplies ordered in Japan with the firm Taihei Kumiai and the Military Attaché in Japan, including letters, certificates, tables, reports, and shipping advice, 1915-1917, concerning the results of tests conducted on artillery supplies (gunpowder, fuses, etc.) ordered from Japanese firms. (Folder 12: 2)
- File No. 55. Correspondence of the Senior Tester and Technical Consultant of the Artillery Committee of the Chief Ordnance Administration (Colonel Podtiagin) with the firm Taihei Kumiai, the Chief Ordnance Administration, and Russian military inspectors and testers in Japan, including letters, information sheets, acts, reports, diagrams, telegrams, requests, and memoranda, 1915-1916, providing information (technical characteristics, quantity, shipping procedures, etc.) on shipments of artillery supplies ordered from Japanese firms, and discussing results of tests conducted on these materials. (Folder 12: 3)
- File No. 56. Letters, telegrams, receipts, lists, tables, bills of lading, insurance policies, invoices, and statements, 1919, relevant to the fulfillment of contracts negotiated by the Chief of the Medical-Veterinary Division of the Far Eastern Military Supply Commission with various Japanese firms for the purchase of surgical instruments and supplies. Includes information on inspection, payment, and shipping. (Folder 12: 4)
- File No. 57. Letters, telegrams, receipts, insurance policies, invoices, reports, and memoranda, 1919, relevant to the fulfillment of contracts negotiated by the Chief of the Medical-Veterinary Division of the Far Eastern Military Supply Commission with various Japanese firms for the purchase of medical instruments and supplies. Includes information on payment and shipping. (Box-folder 13: 1-2)
- File No. 58. 1) Correspondence of the Russian Military Attaché (Major General Podtiagin) including letters, tables, information sheets, accounts, and decrees, 1919, relative to an agreement between the All-Russian Government at Omsk and the Japanese Government for military aid (artillery, medical, engineering, quartermaster, and other supplies) to the Omsk Government, and to the extension of credits from the French Military Mission in Japan, including reports of the various departments of the Far Eastern Military Supply Commission on shipment of these goods. 2) Minutes of the Special Council of the Far Eastern Military Supply Commission. (Folder 13: 3)
- File No. 59. Minutes of the Special Council of the Far Eastern Military Supply Commission, 1919. (Folder 13: 4)
- File No. 60. Letters, contracts, tables, and lists, 1919-1920, relevant to the fulfillment of contracts negotiated by the Chief of the Medical-Veterinary Division of the Far Eastern Military Supply Commission with various Japanese firms for the purchase of surgical instruments and supplies. Includes information on inspection of, and payment for, these goods. (Folder 13: 5)
- File No. 61. Correspondence of the Senior Tester and Technical Consultant of the Artillery Committee of the Chief Ordnance Administration (Colonel Podtiagin) with the Russian Naval Attaché in Japan, Mitsui & Co., the Chief of Artillery at the Vladivostok Fortress, the Chief Ordnance Administration, and the Japanese Naval Ministry, including letters, receipts, reports, information sheets, telegrams, lists, tables, diagrams, and bills of lading, 1915-1916, concerning the purchase of 22-second distance fuses manufactured by the Japanese Naval Ministry according to contract no. 785, and also to the purchase of 3" shrapnel shells and parts for 42-line field artillery. (Box-folder 14: 1)
- File No. 62. Correspondence of the Senior Tester and Technical Consultant of the Artillery Committee of the Chief Ordnance Administration (Colonel Podtiagin) with the Chief of Artillery of the Vladivostok Fortress, the Russian Volunteer Fleet, and the Chief Ordnance Administration, including letters, reports, telegrams, blueprints, minutes, diagrams, and memoranda, 1916-1917, concerning the purchase of 42-line cannon of the 1905 model from the Japanese Naval Ministry, and the packing and shipment of these cannon from the Japanese Naval Arsenal at Kure. (Folder 14: 2)
- File No. 63. Correspondence of the Russian Military Attaché in Japan (Major-General Podtiagin) with the Japan Optical Co., the Chairman of the Far Eastern Military Supply Commission (Lieutenant-General Roop), and his subordinates Lieutenant-Colonel Kostenko and Colonel Popovskii, including letters, telegrams, reports, contracts, and information sheets, 1919-1920, concerning the purchase of 6X binoculars from Japan Optical Co. according to contract nos. 953 and 1149, and the inspection, packing, and shipment of these binoculars. (Folder 14: 3)
- File No. 64. Correspondence of the Russian Military Attaché in Japan (Major-General Podtiagin) with his subordinate, Lieutenant-Colonel Kostenko, and the Japan Optical Co., including letters, accounts, contracts, certificates, insurance policies, reports, and bills of lading, 1919-1920, concerning the purchase of 6X prism binoculars from the Japan Optical Co. according to contract nos. 953 and 1149, and the packing, inspection, and shipment of these binoculars; including copies of contract nos. 953 and 1149. (Folder 14: 4)
- File No. 65. Correspondence of the Senior Tester and Technical Consultant of the Artillery Committee of the Chief Ordnance Administration (Colonel Podtiagin) with the Chief Ordnance Administration and Russian military inspectors and testers in Japan, including letters, reports, receipts, telegrams, certificates, memoranda, accounts, lists, debit advice, and credit advice, 1917-1919, concerning the payment and receipt of salaries to these inspectors, and including instructions for the inspection and preparation for shipment of various ordnance supplies purchased from Japanese firms. (Box-folder 15: 1-2)
- File No. 66. Correspondence of Colonel (later, Major-General) Podtiagin (Senior Tester and Technical Consultant of the Artillery Committee of the Chief Ordnance Administration; Russian Military Attaché in Japan) with the Chief Ordnance Administration, the Russo-Asiatic Bank in Yokahama, the Chairman of the Commission for the Reception of Artillery Supplies Ordered in Japan (Lieutenant-General Somoff), and Russian military inspectors in Japan, including letters, reports, receipts, requests, accounts, credit advice, debit advice, lists, certificates, and passport, 1917-1921, concerning the payment and reception of salaries and travel money to these inspectors, and providing information on income and expenditures from funds at the disposal of Colonel Podtiagin. (Folder 15: 3)
- File No. 67. Correspondence of the Director of Artillery Inspection (General Hermonius) with the Chief of Artillery at the Vladivostok Fortress, the Chief of the Gunpowder Factory at Kazan (General Sagatovskii), the Chief Ordnance Administration, the Russian Imperial Embassy in Tokyo, and the Russian Military Attaché in Japan, including letters, telegrams, and reports, 1914-1915, concerning the inspection, packing, and shipment of artillery supplies (cannon, pistols, camphor) purchased from Japanese firms. (Folder 15: 4)
- File No. 68. Correspondence of the Director of Artillery Inspection (General E. K. Hermonius) with Generals Smyslovskii and Petrovskii of the Chief Ordnance Administration, the Japanese War Office, and the Imperial Russian Embassy in Tokyo, including letters and incoming telegrams, 1914-1915, concerning negotiations for and the conclusion of contracts with Japanese firms for the purchase of artillery supplies, the furnishing of data on these goods, and negotiations with the Japanese War Office concerning purchase of these goods. (Folder 15: 5)
- File No. 69. Rough drafts of telegrams sent by the Director of Artillery Inspection (General E. K. Hermonius) to the Chief Ordnance Administration, 1914-1915. (Box-folder 16: 1)
- File No. 70. Correspondence of the Director of Artillery Inspection (General E. K. Hermonius) with Generals Smyslovskii and Petrovskii of the Chief Ordnance Administration, including letters, telegrams, and rough drafts of telegrams, 1914-1915, concerning negotiations for the purchase of, orders for, inspection, and shipment of military goods purchased from Japanese firms. (Folder 16: 2)
- File No. 71. Memorandum from Admiral Kolchak, undated, regarding his experiences in China with the Russian (anti-bolshevik) armed forces in the area of the Chinese Eastern Railway. (Folder 16: 3)